<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-04-05T15:54:48+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stranger here myself (GCU)</title><subtitle>Opinions expressed here are my own.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">March 2019 books</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/2019/04/04/march-books.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="March 2019 books" /><published>2019-04-04T15:34:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-04T15:34:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/2019/04/04/march-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/2019/04/04/march-books.html">&lt;p&gt;I started reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26195941-the-age-of-surveillance-capitalism&quot;&gt;The Age of Surveillance capitalism&lt;/a&gt; - not very far yet. It’s interesting, but it’s also written in a very academic style - a lot of context and discussion of angles and assumptions, and if I have to be honest, a bit long-winded for me - could do with a TL;DR version. But the nuggets of interesting will keep me coming back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36373688-revenant-gun&quot;&gt;Revenant Gun (Machineries of Empire book 3)&lt;/a&gt;: satisfying last of a trilogy I started reading a while ago. Yoon Ha Lee (american writer) creates an interesting universe, where the laws of physics themselves are influenced by the religious calendar people in that region of space follow. Unfortunately calendars sometime contain ‘remembrances’, ritualized torture, and ‘heretics’ have to be found to offer up on those occasions. A mix of quasi-magical technology, asian baroque and slightly inscrutable battle tactics, it makes for a good adventure read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt9561862/&quot;&gt;Love, death &amp;amp; robots&lt;/a&gt;: shorts TV on Netflix. Format bit like the Twilight Zone, every story detached. Also interesting is the variety of media, from film to CGI to anime to cell shading. Not all equal in quality, but thought provoking, fun and short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For next month, I’ve got the latest Expanse novel (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28335698-tiamat-s-wrath&quot;&gt;Tiamat’s Wrath, number 8&lt;/a&gt;) lined up! Can’t wait, the story keeps on expanding, epically building on the proto-molecule/ancient destroyed civilization context.  The series is scheduled to end with number 9, which is good - would be disappointing to have it fizzle.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I started reading The Age of Surveillance capitalism - not very far yet. It’s interesting, but it’s also written in a very academic style - a lot of context and discussion of angles and assumptions, and if I have to be honest, a bit long-winded for me - could do with a TL;DR version. But the nuggets of interesting will keep me coming back.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chemo halfway point</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cancer/fun/2019/03/19/halfway-point.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chemo halfway point" /><published>2019-03-19T20:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-19T20:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cancer/fun/2019/03/19/halfway-point</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cancer/fun/2019/03/19/halfway-point.html">&lt;p&gt;Halfway point reached for the chemotherapy!  I have 6 cycles of 3 weeks each, and I’ve just emerged from the bad part of the third session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already by the second time the whole thing felt like routine.  Show up, get injected, recover, go back to normal life.
It gets a little harder that way: coming out of the hospital with the certainty that you’re going to feel like crap for the next 5 days (and a little fragile for 2 more days). No novelty factor, no ‘I wonder what’s gonna happen now’, just sticking it out, is hard on the mood. My meditation practice helps a bit, I think I’ll do a blog post about that at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you emerge, it’s like the sun comes out and everything’s great again! You never appreciate health until you go without.  Two weeks out of three is really not bad, considering it gives me a good chance to come out on the other side ready for another good stretch of life. The scans show it’s working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adventure continues: for the next 3 cycles I’ll get a different drugs, Docetaxel, with a slightly different but equally joyful panel of side effects. But first: two whole weeks of normal! Amazing.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Halfway point reached for the chemotherapy! I have 6 cycles of 3 weeks each, and I’ve just emerged from the bad part of the third session.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hair - part 2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cancer/hair/2019/03/13/hair-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hair - part 2" /><published>2019-03-13T15:05:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-13T15:05:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cancer/hair/2019/03/13/hair-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cancer/hair/2019/03/13/hair-part-2.html">&lt;p&gt;After the first chemotherapy session, about 2 weeks in, I lost a lot of hair. Every time I brushed my hair my brush had a generous wad of hair. I had to unclog the shower drain repeatedly, and to remove hair from my clothes. I could still pass for normal, no bald spots, but my hair got quite a bit thinner and I’ve got a slight skrillex on the sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw the writing on the wall, and started investigating options: I bought a couple of chemo hats - fabric head covers - and a couple of proper hats (a Fedora and a Baker Boy, I’ve learned a bit about hats in the last 3 months). Alice quite likes one of my chemo hats, inexplicably, and has taken to wearing it in bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But: in the second cycle of chemo, almost nothing fell out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like some sort of Darwinian culling happened the first time - the weaker hairs got weeded out and what remains are the tough scrappy ones that are hanging on. Looks like the cooling cap is working! Cross fingers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">After the first chemotherapy session, about 2 weeks in, I lost a lot of hair. Every time I brushed my hair my brush had a generous wad of hair. I had to unclog the shower drain repeatedly, and to remove hair from my clothes. I could still pass for normal, no bald spots, but my hair got quite a bit thinner and I’ve got a slight skrillex on the sides.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">February 2019 books</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/media/2019/03/07/february-books.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="February 2019 books" /><published>2019-03-07T20:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-07T20:13:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/media/2019/03/07/february-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/media/2019/03/07/february-books.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6452798-command-and-control&quot;&gt;Command and Control&lt;/a&gt;, a book about the nuclear arms race, has been on my list for a long time, and I finally got round to it.  It’s thorough, nerdy, and well put together.  Without expressing a political view directly, it manages to convey the absurdity of the development and deployment of ever more destructive weaponry.  Actual real life horror, humans at their worst and their most stupid.  Darwin awards at a planetary level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7767021-who-fears-death&quot;&gt;Who fears death&lt;/a&gt; was this month’s book club book. I wasn’t that taken with Binti which was YA, but this story is definitely not for children. It’s the life story of a young woman born from rape, who has extraordinary powers and an epic destiny. The setting is Africa in either the distant past or the far future, with two ethnic groups, one bent on exterminating the other. It manages to be harrowing, a page turner and thought-provoking all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/8667848-a-discovery-of-witches&quot;&gt;A discovery of witches&lt;/a&gt; don’t trust Kindle recommendations - this was the miss of the month. It reads like paranormal romance between cardboard cut-outs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooklyn_Nine-Nine&quot;&gt;Brooklyn Nine-Nine&lt;/a&gt;  Late to this party, I tried a few episodes a while ago and wasn’t convinced.  But I pushed through after my brother talked me into it and saw the light.  Small nuggets of well-scripted joy - back to the mood engineering, this does the trick on a slumpy midweek evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For march I have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/26195941-the-age-of-surveillance-capitalism&quot;&gt;The Age of Surveillance Capitalism&lt;/a&gt; on my list, it sounds like an intriguing read, I’m looking forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Command and Control, a book about the nuclear arms race, has been on my list for a long time, and I finally got round to it. It’s thorough, nerdy, and well put together. Without expressing a political view directly, it manages to convey the absurdity of the development and deployment of ever more destructive weaponry. Actual real life horror, humans at their worst and their most stupid. Darwin awards at a planetary level.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hair</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/23/hair.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hair" /><published>2019-02-23T14:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-23T14:45:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/23/hair</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/23/hair.html">&lt;p&gt;It was pretty much a given from the start that hair loss was a very, very common side effect of the chemo. It fits neatly into the trope of ‘cancer patient’, and it turns out that one is based on reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What wasn’t clear to me is that it’s gradual. I basically expected it all to fall out over a couple of days - but that’s not how it works. Every time I brush my hair, every time I touch it, some hair comes out. Not much, but definitely more than usual - I’d say I find a month’s worth of hair in my brush every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comes its own fun mental hamster wheel. When is the hair loss too much?  Does it still look normal?  Is my scalp starting to shine through?  What is the point where I just give up and cut it all off? (a pro tip I got from a relative is to not go for the full shave but keep a bit of short hair)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m starting to see how a lot of people must get tired of waiting - choosing the ‘sod it’ solution rather than keeping on going with the chinese water torture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s many much worse things in life than to lose one’s hair, it feels silly to be preoccupied with it, but there it is.  Maybe I’m lucky to be have that mental space - things can’t be too bad when you can still worry about your appearance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It was pretty much a given from the start that hair loss was a very, very common side effect of the chemo. It fits neatly into the trope of ‘cancer patient’, and it turns out that one is based on reality.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/18/template.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2019-02-18T20:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-18T20:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/18/template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/18/template.html"></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mirror mirror</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/18/mirror-mirror.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mirror mirror" /><published>2019-02-18T20:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-18T20:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/18/mirror-mirror</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/18/mirror-mirror.html">&lt;p&gt;Our outward identity is a mix of what we perceive our personality is, and our looks.
Some factors are chosen, like clothing, hairstyle, attitude.  Some are not, like age, birth sex, early education, compulsions, phobias, sexual orientation.
We start off a mixed bag of stuff and then we put the face on it that we think reflects the best who we are, or want to be.  Who we think we are may differ significantly from how others see us, but that’s another story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roundabout way to get to the point: having cancer throws another interesting factor in the combination.  How do I see myself now?  How will others see me?  Is ‘cancer’ going to be an important piece of who I am, of how people talk to me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping my hair has actually given me some time to mull it over.  The moment it’s gone I’ll be clearly identifiable.  As a man you can get away with being bald - I’ll go as far as saying that it can be quite attractive. As a woman, unless you’re of the biker-tattoo-piercing persuation, it’s not by choice.  You need a great bone structure to get away with it (i.e. Charlize Theron, Alicia Vikander).  For the rest of us going hairless is an immediate pointer that Something Is Wrong. One of the reasons for wanting to keep (some of) my hair is that not having it will probably predetermine pretty much every casual conversation I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit too much hair in my brush this morning …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking to a stranger about cancer: not a conversation starter.  None of your business, really.  Neither is a wheelchair, a cast, bad scars, body weight.  They may be the elephant in the room - but the elephant is in your head. To the other person it’s just reality, everyday’s background. Worse, you’re emphasizing something they didn’t choose and sets them apart. Go with anything else, a dog, a band t-shirt, a book title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: having and/or surviving cancer doesn’t make you a hero.  It just means you got dealt that card. If you’re sane, you want to survive, it’s pretty much a given - most of us have things to live for, and if we don’t we would like to get the chance to change that. Whatever the situation, I’m pretty sure that most humans facing death would just like a little bit more time, please.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Our outward identity is a mix of what we perceive our personality is, and our looks. Some factors are chosen, like clothing, hairstyle, attitude. Some are not, like age, birth sex, early education, compulsions, phobias, sexual orientation. We start off a mixed bag of stuff and then we put the face on it that we think reflects the best who we are, or want to be. Who we think we are may differ significantly from how others see us, but that’s another story.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Staying afloat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/18/staying-afloat.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Staying afloat" /><published>2019-02-18T20:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-18T20:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/18/staying-afloat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/18/staying-afloat.html">&lt;p&gt;So far, so good -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;meditation&quot;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been practicing meditation for the last couple of years - I use the phone app Headspace for convenience.
Fun fact: there’s actually a ‘Coping with Cancer’ pack in Headspace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is meditation very useful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when you have cancer (and in many other situations) it doesn’t pay to look ahead, or to dwell in the past.  Much to easy to speculate and increase anxiety. Staying in the now is incredibly effective in keeping calm.  And let’s face it, the now is usually a pretty good place to be, it’s not like we live in a post-apocalyptic hell.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interrupting emotional loops: have you ever noticed that it’s very easy to get angrier when angry, or to get more anxious or sad when you already are?  We have a kind of feedback mechanism going, where we validate for ourselves how we feel, and in doing so discover even more reasons to be angry/sad/anxious. Being able to interrupt those loops is very, very handy. Also works against earworms, so extra bonus there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tentatively: there is some experimental evidence that meditation can actually improve the healing process. At a basic level, I guess it’s plain common sense that someone calm who manages to sleep full nights will have more energy to get better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exercise&quot;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nurses and my family all agreed that I needed to pace myself once starting chemo. So I took it to heart and behaved as if I was made of fine china - which turned out to be a little excessive. I feel mostly fine for 2 weeks out of three, so I can definitely some cardio in.  Sure, I’m not going to run marathons (wasn’t before anyway), and the chemo probably acts like the opposite of doping, but exercise is a massive mood booster. I started feeling better as soon as I got back on the bandwagon.
I get yoga at work, and that’s pretty good as well, as an extra relaxation technique and a way to stretch out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;maslows-pyramid&quot;&gt;Maslow’s pyramid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s not forget: an important cause of stress (besides, you know, the disease) are the practicalities. Will this cause me my job? Will we be able to pay rent? Can I ensure my loved one have a reasonably comfortable lifestyle? What if I’m incapacitated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky. I changed jobs in October (well, I was sort of forced to) to a large company. Large companies have the capacity and the procedures to deal with health crises, and benefits include insurance against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Macmillan Cancer helps people finding benefits in case they don’t have a stable income or financial difficulties. In any case, it is a good idea to start looking into it early on, for two reasons: sometimes the treatment can take its toll and make it harder to concentrate on those things, and the paperwork can also take time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;friends-and-family&quot;&gt;Friends and Family&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved to Bath only a little less than 3 years ago. I worked remotely a large chunk of that time, and not being the most socially egregious person in the world, I’m only starting to build a modest network of acquaintances.
But I have a supportive husband and a daughter, so at least I’m not alone - and my extended family is in touch frequently.
I can’t imagine what it must be like to go through this kind of thing alone, with nobody to talk to. Definitely need that occasional chat and lots of hugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;food&quot;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve long classified my acquaintances between two groups: the people who love food, its taste, its texture, for whom food is an integral part of enjoying life, and the people who find it an inconvenience and would rather drink a nutrient brew or take a pill so that they can get on with other more interesting things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve long thought I was somewhere on the spectrum close to the first category: I love food but when I’m hungry I’ll pretty much eat anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple model doesn’t take an important dimension into account: appetite. Soon after the chemo the appetite goes. Turns out I’m pretty weird, in that I still enjoy taste and texture of food, even when I’m slightly queasy. I’ve learned to plan to tasty foods especially in the days right after chemo, because otherwise it’s hard work to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go even further, I still really enjoy cooking, and reading my favourite food porn, Delicious magazine, and plotting future food adventures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;normal&quot;&gt;Normal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And again, saved by that fantastic narrow focus we humans have. We wouldn’t be able to function if we thought of our mortality, the very probable extinction of our race or crumbling of our civilization, the fact that we’re just a tiny blip in time and space.
Fortunately we’re very good at forgetting all of that big picture stuff and focusing on what’s in front of us.
I’m saved by routine: taking care of my daughter, working, household, the normal stuff. Plenty there to keep the brain occupied, and forget about the tricksy cells most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So far, so good -</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">January 2019 books</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/scifi/film/2019/02/09/january-books.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="January 2019 books" /><published>2019-02-09T14:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-09T14:25:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/scifi/film/2019/02/09/january-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/scifi/film/2019/02/09/january-books.html">&lt;p&gt;Continuing the trend of fairly light and cheerful literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/42385018-minimum-wage-magic&quot;&gt;Minimum Wage Magic (DFZ book 1)&lt;/a&gt; I enjoyed Rachel Aaron’s Heartstriker series, full of peppy characters and various creatures who’re really only waiting for the opportunity to be nice people.  Optimistic and fun, and light weight.  This is set in the same universe, but maybe 50 years in the future, and while I didn’t necessarily take the the characters as much as I did to Julius the nice dragon and his friend Marcy, it was still a good action-packed read in the same general spirit, and with the same imagination backing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/35519101-rogue-protocol&quot;&gt;Rogue Protocol: The Murderbot Diaries&lt;/a&gt; Third installment of The Murderbot Diaries.  Murderbot really wants to be left alone to watch entertainment in piece, its real passion in life, but the world and its own conscience won’t let it.  It decides to get involved once more by finding damning evidence against GrayCris, the evil corporation which tried to do away with the team it was protecting in the first book.  Alternate bits of situational humor - Murderbot eyerolls a lot at what stupid humans get up to - and also some good fighty bits, which is after all what Murderbot was created for before it hacked itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Un_Lun_Dun&quot;&gt;Un Lun Dun&lt;/a&gt; China Mieville does it again and creates a delightfully different world in this YA novel.  UnLondon is an abcity, basically the place everything slips to when it’s obsolete in the real London.  That means lots of trash and old tech, but also people.  On top of some top notch world building, the novel constantly plays and defies the fantasy tropes: a Prophecy with a Chosen One, it all gets turned on its head by an intelligent and determined young girl who keeps on questioning assumptions and thinking outside the rules.  I’ll definitely read that one to Alice when she’s a bit older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16096824-a-court-of-thorns-and-roses&quot;&gt;A Court of Thorn and Roses&lt;/a&gt; My miss of the month.  Really I should have known better: I read “Throne of Glass” a good while ago and found it pretty irritating and bad.  But it was YA, while this is classified as decidedly adult, so I thought I’d give it a go.  Sarah J Maas seems to like her protagonists to be impulsive and prone to high drama, and once again there’s a trite love triangle in the making.  I’ll give the sequels a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt6966692/&quot;&gt;Green Book&lt;/a&gt; a film - we don’t go to the movies very often, mostly because babysitting explodes the overall cost of any evening out. We shelled out the night before chemo - YOLO - and didn’t regret it.  “Green Book” is not necessarily a movie that you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to see at the cinema, as in it’s not an action-packed CGI-decorated fast-paced flick, but it’s a great feel good movie in the noblest sense of the word.  The characters are utterly believable and extremely well acted, and there are a lot of fun and moving moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next month there’ll be some non fiction as well as the usual fare, now I know life carries on more or less as usual I’d like to go back to stimulating my brain on the odd occasion.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Continuing the trend of fairly light and cheerful literature.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Better living through chemistry</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/04/better-living-through-chemistry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Better living through chemistry" /><published>2019-02-04T19:57:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-04T19:57:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/04/better-living-through-chemistry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cancer/2019/02/04/better-living-through-chemistry.html">&lt;p&gt;So what’s chemo like?  A question I definitely asked myself with some anxiety a week ago.
The whole thing started the day before, with having to take anti-sickness pills.  Amongst those pills were some steroids, which, to put it mildly, work like a stimulant for me.  For three days I was literally ‘on steroids’ - enough to put me off any kind of stimulants for a while (yes, even you, caffeine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day itself I was shown to a comfy and easily cleanable fake leather armchair in a sunny hospital ward.  Joe sat next to me, being a great moral support, checking up on me and tapping away on his laptop (working remotely ftw).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opted to use the ‘cooling cap’.  It is basically a hat made of rubber tubes - very Dr Who - and a machine located next to the chair pumps cold water through the tubes, cooling the surface of your head.  Why?  Well, in 50% of cases, “you keep enough hair for it to be worth it”.
Not a watertight sell for the cap, and it sounds even less appealing when you know it adds about two hours to the total duration of the chemo: you cool your head for 30 minutes before the injections, and then you keep it on for 90 minutes after.  I’m still pondering whether it’s worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, a friendly nurse inserted a perfusion into my arm, and then proceeded to inject three full seringes of red stuff (Epirubicin) into it.  I was given some ice lollies to avoid mouth sores, which the red stuff causes at injection time.  The nurse kept asking me questions about my life - in hindsight she probably wasn’t that interested in my job, but was distracting me or checking up on my general brain function.  I felt a little bit fuzzy, but not that much, considering I my brain was being undercooled.
The next thing on the menu was a clear bag of liquid (5 fluorouracil), hung up to drip into the perfusion for a bit, while the cooling cap machine continued to buzz next to me.
And that was it!  A mere three hours later, feeling much the same, I walked out into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the aftermath: putting it bluntly, reading the side effects brought to mind the image of a Chernobyl victim.  Bleeding gums, hairloss, loss of appetite, fatigue, nausea … the reality was much less dramatic for me.
The same evening I felt a bit nauseous, and that queasiness continued, low-level, for the next couple of days.  It didn’t take me that long to decode the feeling as ‘hungry’ or ‘take it easy’.  Between that and the steroids startling me awake at odd hours of the night, I was tired, wired and queasy for a few days, but once I could sleep well again, I felt better pretty quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today, I finally realized that the only abnormal thing left, a tension in my chest, was actually a low-level feeling of dread I’d been carrying since the injections. I was able to breathe more freely, and to laugh at myself a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I understand the principle of chemo is that it slows the rate of multiplication of cells pretty dramatically.  This means various blood cells counts go down (my immune system is hit), my hair and nails won’t grow as they usually do, wounds won’t heal as quickly.  I expect it will get harder as time wears on.  But for now, I’m doing well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">So what’s chemo like? A question I definitely asked myself with some anxiety a week ago. The whole thing started the day before, with having to take anti-sickness pills. Amongst those pills were some steroids, which, to put it mildly, work like a stimulant for me. For three days I was literally ‘on steroids’ - enough to put me off any kind of stimulants for a while (yes, even you, caffeine).</summary></entry></feed>