<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-06T21:57:06+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stranger here myself (GCU)</title><subtitle>Opinions expressed here are solely my own.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Is this going to be a cancer blog?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/meta/cancer/2019/01/04/big-c.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is this going to be a cancer blog?" /><published>2019-01-04T21:32:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-04T21:32:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/meta/cancer/2019/01/04/big-c</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/meta/cancer/2019/01/04/big-c.html">&lt;p&gt;I got the news on Thursday: the lump is not friendly.  I’m going to have to undergo surgery, chemo and radiotherapy.
I wonder if the doctors practice that grave expression in the mirror, I mean, when you have to dish out that kind of news on a regular basis, you must acquire a little bit of distance, you can’t feel it that keenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As cancers go it’s not the worst: breast cancer is super common and has benefited from a lot of research. The stats are pretty good - if I caught it in time.  Which I’m not yet sure about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course I notified my whole family - wrote them a group email. In the next few hours I realized that the news is harder on the people who love me than it is on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I’m fine.  Really!  I’m just as healthy as I was 3 days ago.  ‘Asymptomatic’ they call it - you literally have no effect at all.  I have a very good chance of making it out.  I’m in a country with good and cheap/free healthcare.  I’ve got a lot of supports from all sides. I might not feel as sanguine or as positive in a few weeks or months, when I’m missing bits of my anatomy and I’m knocked down by aggressive drugs, but for now, I’m OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read in one of the many, many NHS brochures that people’s first reaction is ‘why me?’.  That didn’t really occur to me - statistically, some people are going to be it, and why not me?  It strikes me as the reaction of people who have never had anything bad happen to them or their relatives - good for them I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first feeling is irritation and stress.  Some longer-term projects are completely on hold.  Financially things are going to be a little bit more interesting to juggle (although work has been great). I want my family, my daughter to be ok, to be happy and carefree - and all I can do for now is mitigate the fallout.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I got the news on Thursday: the lump is not friendly. I’m going to have to undergo surgery, chemo and radiotherapy. I wonder if the doctors practice that grave expression in the mirror, I mean, when you have to dish out that kind of news on a regular basis, you must acquire a little bit of distance, you can’t feel it that keenly.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Year - New Blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/meta/2019/01/02/happy-2019.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Year - New Blog" /><published>2019-01-02T21:32:31+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-02T21:32:31+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/meta/2019/01/02/happy-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/meta/2019/01/02/happy-2019.html">&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of other people, I did blog a fair bit in the mid naughties - that’s what you did, back then.  Facebook was taking off, but wasn’t anywhere near what it is now (that is, trying to be everything to everyone). Twitter was also growing, but was still mostly marginal.  Instagram wasn’t there yet, snapshat either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blogging was a less constrained version of a timeline - it was the way you told the world how you were, what you were thinking, what cool tech you were working on this week. You had a number of followers (mostly people you knew) who would comment, and small discussions would take place.  Is it weird that it feels like it was a more innocent time?  Or maybe I was just oblivious of the darker corners of the web and the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter took over for me.  It was faster, easier, no maintenance.  You could follow people you admired quite easily.  It became fun to compose pithy, 140 character snippets, putting as much wit and skill as possible.  Soon the blog withered and died - I hadn’t put in the maintenance effort, and the last blog post lay there gathering dust while the engine got more and more out of date and I missed weeks of downtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I realized that I missed long form.  Writing 140 characters just doesn’t require a lot of, well, thought - you don’t need to work out pros, cons, different point of views.  You hit and run.  And that may lead to laziness of thought - longer text just require you to dig a little more, and to quote sources, and reflect on those sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s the growing realization that once you tweet, you’re giving away your content to be profited from. It’s curated, reordered and presented so that the company can generate maximum advertizement revenue.  It may be aggregated and sold and analyzed by political influencers and marketers - and generally be used in ways you’d not want it to be.  If twitter don’t like what you say or who you are, they can simply cut off the flow, and you have no way to appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decentralized web we started whispering about in the naughties now seems more and more urgent and relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More simply I like the freedom of just dumping stuff in whatever shape I like in a blog, for my enjoyment and archives just as much as anyone else’s.  I make no commitment on how often I’ll blog or what it’ll be.
I just want my own little corner back.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Like a lot of other people, I did blog a fair bit in the mid naughties - that’s what you did, back then. Facebook was taking off, but wasn’t anywhere near what it is now (that is, trying to be everything to everyone). Twitter was also growing, but was still mostly marginal. Instagram wasn’t there yet, snapshat either.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/01/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2019-01-01T21:32:31+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-01T21:32:31+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/01/01/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/01/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry></feed>